# ROBBIE WALLER, MENG. (HONS) PGDIP

☑ rob@robbiewaller.co.uk

 $\Box +447523207689$ 

## PERSONAL STATEMENT

I have worked as a nuclear engineer and operator with the Royal Navy since 2011. I am seeking opportunities to work in the operational side of Nuclear Power generation in the UK and beyond.

I am enthusiastic, self motivating and independent. I have broad experience of operating 3 different Pressurised Water Reactors in the UK and USA.

# **EDUCATION**

MENG (HONS), MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHAMPTON	2011
POSTGRADUATE DIPLOMA, CRANFIELD UNIVERSITY, NUCLEAR REACTOR TECHNOLOGY	2013
Engineering Charge Qualification, Naval Reactors, Washington DC	2018

## **EXPERIENCE**

#### SUBMARINE ASSURANCE OFFICER, NAVY COMMAND

2018-PRESENT

- Responsible for providing assurance that the submarine service operates within its nuclear authorisation conditions and the health, safety and environmental constraints of the Defence Maritime Regulator (DMR).
- Acted as regulator-facing individual, conducting regular 3rd party audits on subordinate organisations. Identified, managed and corrected nuclear non-compliance findings as well as DMR findings.
- Learning from Experience' (LfE) champion for the submarine service. Conducted independent study into engineering LfE, identifying, tracking and closing recommendations.

## SAFETY DELIVERY MANAGER, NUCLEAR PROPULSION PROJECT TEAM, MOD 2017 - 2018

- Project lead for a nuclear engineering safety case development program. Responsible for interpreting experimental and calculated data to provide recommendations on safety case limitations for future operation.
- Responsible for amalgamating the results of studies conducted by Rolls Royce and Wood group to make recommendations to the Defence Nuclear Safety Regulator that plants are safe to operate, extending the operational life of 2 nuclear plants.
- Acted as Assistant Duly Authorised Person (ADAP).

#### **ELECTRICAL OFFICER & ASSISTANT ENGINEER**

2016-2018

- Sole British crew member on the USS Hartford, a Los-Angeles Class fast attack submarine on operations including surfacing at North Pole.
- 2000 hours experience as Qualified Critical plant supervisor and 50 days of experience as Shutdown plant supervisor. 6 successful reactor startups and shutdowns as plant supervisor.
- Responsible for \$1.5 billion submarine alongside, managing a 25-person team for 24-hour periods.
- Direct management responsibility for 15 nuclear electricians, coordinating the response to unplanned defects as well as supervising all electrical maintenance activities onboard.

- Passed professional examinations and interviews at Naval Reactors in Washington DC (PNEO), giving certification to operate as the Chief Engineer on a USN nuclear plant.
- Qualified as a Duly Authorised Person (DAP), providing oversight to complex nuclear operations such as cool downs, control rod testing, switchboard maintenance and live plant drill periods.

#### SUBMARINE SUSTAINABLE MANNING PROGRAM

2015 - 2016

- Facilitated a study with PA Consulting, analysing novel ways of staffing Nuclear control rooms with contractors during maintenance periods.
- Conducted training needs analysis of a shut-down nuclear operator in order to enable contractorisation. Resulted in 2 contractors undertaking trial periods of nuclear operation on a submarine.

#### **NAVAL NUCLEAR POWER TRAINING COMMAND**

2014-2015

- Selected as top student of 18 candidates on graduate scheme to undertake a prestigious 3-year exchange with the US Navy.
- Undertook 6-months of academically rigorous training before a further 6-month period of rotational shift work on a 'prototype' S5W reactor design at Naval Nuclear Power Training Unit Charleston.
- Certified by the US Navy and the US Department of Energy to be a Nuclear Engineering Officer of the Watch, qualifying early, with above average marks in all assessments.

### **ASSISTANT MARINE ENGINEERING OFFICER (TRAINING)**

2012 - 2014

- Undertook a 2-year Royal Navy graduate scheme, comprising theoretical and practical training in mechanical systems, electronics, refrigeration, nuclear theory, reactor design, nuclear health physics and nuclear systems.
- 6-months of training aboard HMS ASTUTE, where I qualified as an engineering spaces watch-keeper and an electrical panel operator.
- Conducted 3- month period of independent research into a Tritium monitoring facility in a radiochemistry lab. Designed, ran and evaluated experiments using a Liquid Scintillation Counter (LSC) resulting in the development of standard operating procedures and commissioning for future testing.
- Conducted a technical review of 'state-of-the-art' LSC techniques for solid sampling, the output of which was a presentation to an industry partner on methods for optimising their 'tritium analysis in solids' techniques.

#### FRENCH NAVAL ACADEMY, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING STUDENT

2010

- Studied mechanical engineering in the French speaking École Navale as part of undergraduate degree.
- Achieved a working level of fluency in technical and conversational French.

## **FURTHER INFORMATION**

- Professional Memberships: Chartered Engineer, Institute of Mechanical Engineering (Submitted, awaiting interview)
- Security Cleared to a high government standard
- Interests: RYA Yachtmaster Instructor, Motorcycles, conversational German.